JOE: Children and young people
with autism can be very intense
and focused about favourite toys,
activities and topics of conversation.
They may collect things and follow
repetitive actions when entering a room.
Some individuals might have very narrow
interests or preoccupations, like needing
to know everything possible about trains.
BETH: Sensory sensitivities can also lead
to developing obsessions and rituals.
Children might like to stroke people’s
hair whenever they can because they enjoy
the sensation, or it helps them feel calm.
Children with autism can get upset
when they can’t do their obsessive
behaviour, routines or rituals.
JOE: Using obsessions or special
interests to help control behaviour can
make the experience more pleasurable.
For example, when a parent gets a
young child to eat by pretending
the food is a train and their mouth
is a tunnel, this approach can be
used with individuals with autism.
By using their obsession or special
interest in something, creatively,
they can be encouraged to do something
they wouldn’t want too normally.
BETH: Finding a positive outlet for an
obsessive interest, for example, if an
individual has an interest in dinosaurs,
they might be more inclined to go to a
museum to see fossils or eat food with
a link to dinosaurs on the packaging.
JOE: Also, obsessions and special
interests of individuals with autism
can be used as rewards and motivators to
help teach them new skills and behaviour.
If they complete a task or activity
or experience something new, they can
have more time doing what they love.